Okay, good morning, חג פורים שמח. Chag Purim Sameach. We pick up
on מ"א. Mem Aleph. We're in the middle of the דף, daf,
so we're actually a good bit ahead. And we start with the
משנה. Mishna. Thankfully the שמיטה Shemitta discussions are a bit behind us.
So we pick up with the משנה. Mishna. בראשונה היה לולב ניטל
במקדש שבעה ובמדינה יום אחד. Barishona hayah lulav nital bamikdash shiva u-vamedina
yom echad. So quite interestingly, we spent the whole פרק perek discussing
the objects of לולב lulav and the אתרוג, etrog,
and then where you would do the shaking at הלל Hallel and
so on. And finally at the end, then even special cases of
the שמיטה Shemitta case, and then finally, finally we get to the
issue of what actually is the nature of the obligation. So in
the originally the לולב lulav was taken in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash for all seven days, and in the מדינה medina for one
day. Now what's the מדינה? medina? So presumably in contrast to the
מקדש, mikdash, it means anywhere outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
However, interestingly, רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot in this case
and in one or two other cases when there's מקדש mikdash is
contrasted to מדינה medina says that it refers to outside of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, that מקדש mikdash really means anywhere within ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So for
example, you have a similar משנה Mishna that they would blow the
לולב—blow lulav the לולב, lulav, blow, that was not meant, that was
just a עד דלא ידע, ad delo yada, right exactly, they would
blow the שופר shofar on ראש השנה Rosh Hashana that fell out
on שבת Shabbos in the מקדש mikdash but not in the מדינה,
medina, and for the רמב"ם Rambam that includes not only the מקדש
mikdash but also ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But here as well he understands that
it means the מקדש mikdash and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Most of course understand
that it means literally just the מקדש mikdash and outside of the
מקדש. mikdash. So seven days in the מקדש, mikdash, why? Based on
the verse that says ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון, v'likachtem lachem bayom harishon,
take for yourself on the first day, פרי עץ הדר כפות תמרים
וענף עץ עבות וערבי נחל, pri etz hadar kapot temarim v'anaf etz
avot v'arvei nachal, so that's day one, it's a day one מצווה.
mitzvah. And then the end of the verse says ושמחתם לפני ה'
אלקיכם שבעת ימים, v'semachtem lifnei Hashem elokeichem shivat yamim, rejoice before Hashem
your God for seven days. So there's a seven-day מצווה mitzvah that
is understood to also be a מצווה mitzvah of the לולב, lulav,
and that is לפני ה' אלקיכם, lifnei Hashem elokeichem, in front of
Hashem your God, which means in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, or
according to the רמב"ם Rambam the מקדש mikdash and its environs, מקדש
mikdash and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But that is seven days. So originally it
was a seven-day מצווה mitzvah in the מקדש mikdash and outside of
the מקדש mikdash for one day.
משנחרב בית המקדש, mish-necherav beit hamikdash, once the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
was destroyed, התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי hitkin raban yochanan ben zakai
שיהא לולב ניטל במדינה שבעה. she-yehei lulav nital bamedina shiva. רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Raban Yochanan ben Zakai said that the לולב lulav should
be taken all seven days, not just everywhere, because now it would
never be taken in the מקדש mikdash for seven days because there
was no longer a מקדש. mikdash. So take it everywhere for seven
days, זכר למקדש, zecher lamikdash, as a way to remember the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. ויהא יום הנף כולו אסור, v'yehei yom hanaf kulo
asur, and the day of the waving of the עומר omer should
be fully forbidden. So it's quite fascinating why are we mentioning the
bringing of the עומר, omer, the waving of the עומר? omer? But
תוספות Tosafot says, well, maybe these two were sort of set at
the same time. There's a lot of תקנות takanot רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי Raban Yochanan ben Zakai made זכר למקדש, zecher lamikdash, these are
only two of them, these are the two that are mentioned in
our משנה. Mishna. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara interestingly completely ignores the fascinating point about the לולב,
lulav, is it a one-day מצווה mitzvah or seven-day מצווה? mitzvah? In
a way that'll get discussed in the beginning of the next פרק,
perek, and it jumps totally just to the idea of זכר למקדש.
zecher lamikdash. מנלן דעבדינן זכר למקדש, minalan d'avdinan zecher lamikdash, says the
גמרא, Gemara, where do you get this idea that you should do
something to remember the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? אמר רבי יוחנן אמר
קרא, amar rabi yochanan amar k'ra, רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says because
the verse says, כי אעלה ארוכה לך וממכותיך ארפאך, ki a'aleh aruchah
lach u-mimakotayich erpa-echa, because I will raise up a healing for you
and from your wounds I will heal you, נאום ה', ne'um Hashem,
says God, כי נדחה קראו לך, ki nidchah kar'u lach, because a
castaway they have called you,
ציון היא דורש אין לה, Tziyon hee doreish ein lah, no one
seeks after it. So like bemoaning the fate of ירושלים Yerushalayim after
the חורבן. churban. So it says no one is seeking after it.
דורש אין לה, doreish ein lah, no one is seeking after it,
מכלל דבעי דרישה, miklal d'ba'i doreish, that we should be seeking after
it, we should be things to remember the חורבן churban of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. I just want to say this is a larger discussion, but
I wrote an article once which to me
is surprised that nobody had ever said it before, but I think
it's a profound appreciation of what רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Raban Yochanan
ben Zakai is doing. You know we always talk about רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Raban Yochanan ben Zakai being concerned about the חורבן הבית
churban habayit and making sure that it's in the forefront of our
consciousness and so on. But first of all, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי,
Raban Yochanan ben Zakai, if you think about it, was the one
that actually helped the Jewish people at the wake of the חורבן
churban transition away from a מקדש mikdash centered Judaism to a תורה
Torah centered Judaism, right? He was the one that according to the
מדרש Midrash went out to make a peace with Vespasian and he
says—it's a whole story in גמרא Gemara גיטין, Gittin, I'm not saying
it's historical, but my concern is more the message of it—that Vespasian
at the end of it says, ask for me one thing and
I'll give it to you, and he said, תנו לי יבנה וחכמיה,
tnu lee Yavne v'chachameha, give me יבנה. Yavne. and its wise men.
And then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, oh, he was so stupid,
he should have asked to save ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, he figured that was a lost cause and if
he asks for that it's not going to happen, so he might
as well ask for יבנה, Yavneh, which to me is a perfect
distillation of two different approaches, like one is always bemoaning the מקדש
Mikdash and the חורבן Churban of the מקדש Mikdash and even at
the last minute even when it's already a still a lost cause
all you can think about is what are we going to do
to save the מקדש Mikdash and completely is looking at that and
once the מקדש Mikdash is of course destroyed then it focuses it's
on the absence of the מקדש, Mikdash, whereas יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan
ben Zakkai was able to have the foresight to know when it
was time to cut your losses and to move forward and to
take a new tack and a new approach and let's not be
focused on the past and on the מקדש Mikdash and let's figure
out what we're doing to move forward and let's focus on יבנה
Yavneh and like a תורה Torah centered Judaism. And it plays out
in other ways as well, the famous story where you know they're
walking by ירושלים Yerushalayim and they see the foxes coming from הר
הבית Har Habayit and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva laughs and they say
why are you laughing and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says well once
the prophecy that the מקדש Mikdash would be destroyed was fulfilled and
the foxes were going to go on הר הבית, Har Habayit, I
know that in the end the prophecy that it'll be rebuilt will
also be fulfilled. Okay which is very nice which is a very
positive and optimistic view but it still focuses on the fact that
you know we're going to get the מקדש Mikdash again, that the
מקדש Mikdash is still very central you know as opposed to a
similar story which יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai had as reported
in אבות דרבי נתן Avos de-Rabbi Noson where they're walking by the
הר הבית Har Habayit and they see the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash
is destroyed and יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai is laughing and
his students surprised say well why are you laughing? And he says
well what do you think like all we have is the
מקדש, Mikdash, better than מיכה Micah says, all we have is the
מקדש Mikdash you know to as a way of sort of you
know worshipping God? We have other things that are that are you
know that are that are equal to the מקדש Mikdash because the
verse says you know because because the verse basically says חסד חפצתי
ולא זבח, Chesed chafatzti v’lo zavach, I want your loving kindness not
your sacrifices you know and we have prayer and we have תורה
Torah and מעשים טובים Ma'asim Tovim which you know which are you
know which God wants you know more than the sacrifices. So again
the point being not that we have things that somehow are substitute
and the מקדש Mikdash is the all that it's about and these
are somehow make up for it, but there actually is a different
way of focusing where our sort of center of religious practice should
be. So יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai actually is quite interesting.
So if you think about that and then you think that he's
the one that does זכר למקדש, Zecher l'Mikdash, it's a little funny
except that his זכר למקדש Zecher l'Mikdash and this is sort of
my thesis is actually does has the opposite effect of what it
ostensibly comes to do. It ostensibly comes to help remind us of
the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and the loss of the בית המקדש,
Beis ha-Mikdash, but if I were to go around to you today
and said you know why do we take the לולב lulav for
seven days what would your answer probably be? The answer would probably
be what do you mean why do we take it for seven
days it's a מצוה mitzvah to take the לולב lulav for seven
days right? It's not like taking it on the other days makes
us remember oh we're doing this to remember that we used to
have a בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and we used to, no actually
maybe you think about that when you do the הושענות Hoshanos on
הושענא רבה, Hoshanah Rabbah, but when you actually do this for seven
days it actually it actually
makes you think that who needs the בית המקדש? Beis ha-Mikdash? We
actually have a seven day מצוה mitzvah taking the לולב. lulav. So
it actually has the opposite effect, rather than heightening the loss of
the מקדש Mikdash and reminding us of the מקדש, Mikdash, it actually
creates a religious experience, an expanded religious experience in the absence of
the מקדש, Mikdash, right? So it actually has quite you know the
opposite effect. So that's actually if you go through the various תקנות
takanos of יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai that are that are
sort of ascribed given the purpose of set for the purpose of
זכר למקדש, Zecher l'Mikdash, the real effect that they have is to
create a vibrant and in a way almost like a more vibrant
because now everybody is doing it it's not just being done in
the מקדש Mikdash by a few people, Judaism in the absence of
the מקדש Mikdash and we retain the vibrancy we so you know
even in its absence. So I think that it's really there's a
very sort of powerful idea behind יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai
and his relationship to the מקדש Mikdash and the effect that these
תקנות takanos have. Yes.
I actually think that there's even a deepened impact of this theology
when one does know that it's זכר למקדש Zecher l'Mikdash which is
יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai found a way to institute
phenomenologically that the yearning for the מקדש Mikdash is a substitute for
its actuality and it's a more powerful religious motivator to yearn for
something knowing implicitly that it's better that it not be materialized. All
right
that's interesting. All right.
And something.
Okay, anyway, that's an interesting point. So I don't actually think that
my approach is a little different. My approach is that the effect
was actually the effect of taking the לולב lulav seven days
doesn't cultivate a sense of yearning for the מקדש, Mikdash, it actually
supplants any sense of מקדש. Mikdash. So I actually think it's quite
different. But okay, let's take a look. So that was a זכר
למקדש. Zecher L'mikdash. No discussion about the actual idea of לולב lulav
one and seven. We'll discuss that more in the next פרק. perek.
But שיהא יום הנף כולו אסור. Sheyehei yom hanaf kulo asur. The
day of the waving of the עומר Omer should be fully forbidden.
Now, what's the story? The story is that you cannot eat the
new grain until the עומר Omer is brought the second day of
פסח. Pesach. עד יום הביאכם את קרבן אלהיכם. Ad yom havi'achem et
korban Elokeichem.
Until you bring your קרבן, korban, the עומר. Omer. What if no
קרבן korban is brought? So the assumption is if there's not going
to be a קרבן korban because there's no בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
it actually becomes permissible at the beginning of the day. ולחם וקלי
וכרמל לא תאכלו עד עצם היום הזה, V'lechem vekali v'karmel lo tochlu
ad etzem hayom hazeh,
until the essence of this day, which is understood to mean until
the day begins. So ironically, if there's no מקדש, Mikdash, it's permitted
as soon as the day sixteenth of ניסן Nissan begins. If there
is a מקדש, Mikdash, it's only permitted once the עומר Omer is
brought. So why did he say that it would be forbidden the
entire day of the sixteenth with no בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash? Let's
take a look.
The עומר Omer was brought early
in the morning anyway, wasn't it? Well, it was brought by חצות,
chatzot, but not first thing. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason
that he said it's forbidden the whole day? מהרה יבנה בית המקדש,
Meheira yibaneh Beit Hamikdash, quickly the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash should be
rebuilt, ויאמרו v'yomru and they'll say, אשתקד מי לא אכלנו בהאיר מזרח?
Ishtakad mi lo achalnu b'he'ir mizrach? If nowadays you start eating at
daybreak of the sixteenth, then when the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is
rebuilt, people will say, 'Hey, last year we ate it when the
first thing of the sixteenth we had oatmeal of the new grain,
you know, first thing in the morning of the sixteenth,' actually it's
פסח Pesach so okay, whatever, we had the כשר לפסח kosher le'pesach
oatmeal, we had מצות. matzas. השתא נמי ניכול. Hashata nami neichol.
So let's also now eat it the first thing of the sixteenth.
ואינהו לא ידעי V'innu lo yad'i and they won't realize, אשתקד דלא
הוה בית המקדש, Ishtakad d'lo hava Beit Hamikdash, last year there was
no בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash yet, האיר מזרח התיר, he'ir mizrach hitir,
as soon as the east became light, as soon as the day
broke, it became permissible. השתא דאיכא בית המקדש, Hashata d'ika Beit Hamikdash,
now that there is a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, עומר מתיר, Omer
matir, you need the actual bringing of the עומר Omer to make
it permissible. So the גמרא Gemara says, all right, so that's why
we can't eat it the whole day. So the גמרא Gemara says,
דאיבני אימת? D'ivni eimat? When are you afraid? You gotta love these
גמרות Gemaras that bring in the actual scenario of the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash talk about זכר למקדש Zecher L'mikdash being rebuilt for halakhic
analysis. When exactly are you concerned that the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
will be rebuilt in this scenario that they might eat the עומר
Omer a little bit, they might eat the new grain a little
bit too early? אילימא דאיבני בשיתסר, Iyleima d'ivni b'shis'sar,
you're afraid that the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash will be rebuilt on
חול המועד פסח Chol HaMoed Pesach on the sixteenth of ניסן? Nissan?
הרי התיר האיר מזרח. Harei hitir he'ir mizrach. So if it
wasn't, if it was only built later in the day on the
sixteenth, as soon as daybreak occurred on the sixteenth, when there's no
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash wasn't built yet,
it's going to be finished being built later in the day, so
as soon as daybreak the new grain was permissible. So it wouldn't
be a problem to eat it. And the assumption being that by
the time... okay, so let's say. אלא, Ela, so the גמרא Gemara
says, rather, דאיבני בחמישה עשר, d'ivni b'chamesh-esar,
so it was built on the fifteenth, it was built on יום
טוב Yom Tov itself. We'll talk about that in a
minute. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מחצות היום ולהלן ישתרי, Mechatzot hayom u'lehallan yishtarei,
then at least you should be able to eat it from midday,
meaning, why did the גזירה gezeira have to be that you can't
eat the new grain the whole day? Just say wait till midday.
Why? Because התנן, hatnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, הרחוקים, harchokim,
people that live distant from ירושלים, Yerushalayim, מותרים, muttarin, could eat the
new grain, מחצות היום ולהלן, mechatzot hayom u'lehallan, starting at noon, לפי
שאין בית דין מתעצלים בו, lefi she'ein Beit Din mit'atzlim bo, because
בית דין Beit Din was never lazy
to allow the עומר Omer to be brought later than noon. בית
דין Beit Din was always punctual to make sure the עומר Omer
was brought at the very, very latest by noon. So it says,
look, make up your mind. If it's being built already on the
sixteenth, so there wasn't time to bring it earlier, but you know
what, as soon as daybreak, it's going to be permissible. So you're
concerned that it will have been brought
before, built excuse me, built before. So okay, but then in that
case, just have a practice not to eat it till noon, because
we know that whenever there was a בית דין Beit Din they
made sure the עומר Omer was always brought by noon. Why do
you have to have a practice not to eat it the whole
day? Whatever will happen in the future, just have a practice not
to eat it by noon, and whatever will happen in the future
when God willing the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is rebuilt, you'll be
able to eat it by noon. What scenario would you not be
able to eat it by noon? One minute, let's see the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay
look, צריכא, tzricha, you need it for the following scenario. Here's the
scenario where you won't be able to have eaten it by noon.
The בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash will be rebuilt and that day you
won't be able to eat it by noon. What's the scenario? דאיבני
בליליא. D'ivni b'leilya. It was built... It was built on the night
leading into the 16th. Okay, אינמי סמוך לשקיעת החמה, inami samuch lishkias
hachamah,
or right before the sunset of the end of the 15th. Now
what's that scenario? So again, it's being built on יום טוב Yom
Tov and built at night, which I'll talk about in a minute,
but if it's built at the end of, right at let's say
the night leading into the 16th, so when daybreaks on the 16th,
you can't, the day
it's not permissible because there's already a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You
have to wait till the עומר Omer is brought. Fine, bring the
עומר Omer by noon. No. If you only built the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and finished it the night before, then you can't just
wake up and decide we're bringing the עומר. Omer. In order to
bring the עומר Omer was a major process. You had to go
out to the fields, they had to identify which wheat they were
going to cut, they had to cut the wheat, they had to
grind the wheat, they had to do thirteen different processes of sifting
it. So you needed lead time in order to get it done
by noon of that day. So the concern is if we say
you can, you have to wait till noon to eat it, the
concern is the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash will be rebuilt the night
before of the 16th and there won't be, and there'll be because
it'll be built you'll need to wait for the עומר Omer to
be brought, but because it will be built just the night before
there won't be enough lead time and therefore it won't be ready
by noon. And therefore we had to say don't eat it the
whole day. Pretty wild scenario.
Why wouldn't it be by noon if it's built in the morning?
Not those.
If it's the morning of the 16th then as soon as daybreaks
then it's מותר muttar immediately because there's no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
yet. If it was built on the morning of the 15th then
you have a whole day to get ready. But in this one
scenario we therefore have to not eat it the whole day. Sounds
quite wild. Now by the way רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both
say, or רש"י Rashi really, תוספות Tosafos just repeats רש"י, Rashi, I
thought you're not allowed to build a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash at
night, I thought you're not allowed to build a בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So if you take a look
at רש"י, Rashi, so, well that's what רש"י's Rashi answer. So if
you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, you probably remember because רש"י
Rashi said it. So רש"י, Rashi, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
go to the two lines from the bottom, he says, דאין בנין
בית המקדש דוחה יום טוב, de'ein binyan Beis Hamikdash doche Yom Tov,
and also the line before he said it's not built at night.
הני מילי בנין הבנוי בידי אדם. Hani mili binyan habanui bidei adam.
Which, which רש"י? Rashi?
I'm just two lines from the bottom of the רש"י. Rashi. It's
in the middle of a long רש"י. Rashi. הני מילי בנין הבנוי
בידי אדם אבל מקדש העתיד שאנו מצפים בנוי ומשוכלל הוא יגלה ויבא
משמים. Hani mili binyan habanui bidei adam, aval mikdash ha'asid she'anu mitzapin
banui umeshuchlal hu yigale veyavo mishamayim.
The future בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that we're looking towards is already
built and finished and it's ready and it's going to be revealed
from heaven. שנאמר מקדש ה' כוננו ידיך. Shene'emar Mikdash Hashem konenu yadecha.
That's going to be built by God, by you know, which is
quite fascinating in general because about this certain you know approaches towards
redemption. Are you just waiting for it all to come from heaven?
How much do humans take a role in redemption? You know nothing
at all relevant to issues nowadays about Zionism and the role that
we have to play. It's, but historically you know it was actually
true about, I know it's פורים Purim time, but it was actually
true about חנוכה Chanukah as well. You know the חשמונאים Chashmonaim were
you know and
obviously were very righteous but there were even like פרום frum people
around that said you know in the way פרום frummer that said
you know God will redeem us, if God wants salvation then God
is going to do it and we shouldn't be playing a role
in this. And don't defend yourselves on שבת. Shabbos. Yeah well that's
true. So anyway that's quite a fascinating explanation of this גמרא. Gemara.
Yes Michael you had a question.
Why do you think the תוספות Tosafos came in to say because
it's בית דין Beis Din and not מצד הכהנים? mitzad hakohanim?
So when do you think the כהנים? kohanim? Yeah as we discussed
in the past in יומא Yoma and other places, the גמרא Gemara
imagines that all of the things that went on in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash were ultimately under the auspices of בית דין. Beis
Din. So sort of imagines that the rabbis were sort of in
charge of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי בשיטת רבי יהודה אמר. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai beshitas Rabbi Yehuda amar.
Actually that's wrong, it's not a גזירה. gezeira. When he says don't
eat it the whole day he's following the position of רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר מן התורה הוא אסור. de'amar min hatorah hu assur.
It says biblically you're not allowed to eat the new grain if
there's no עומר Omer the entire day. It's not like we've been
assuming that it's allowed at daybreak, it's forbidden the whole day until
the end of the day. דכתיב Dechisiv because the verse said עד
עצם היום הזה, ad etzem hayom hazeh, you shall eat no grain
until the essence of this day, עד עיצומו של יום, ad itzumo
shel yom,
until the very essence of the day. דקסבר עד ועד בכלל. dekasvar
ad ve'ad bechlal.
And עד ad means up to and including. So the new grain
is forbidden up until and including this very day. So the new
grain is forbidden for the entire day. Okay so עד ad does
not mean daybreak. Because no, עצם etzem means the day itself. But
up to the day or up to and including the day?
יומא היום Yoma hayom means the day. So עצם etzem means something
other than a whole day?
No, the entire day. But until, that's what it means, the very
essence, the entire day. But is it, the key is whether it's
up to and including or up to and not including. So he
says it means up to and including. So it's forbidden the entire
day. Unless there's the עומר, Omer, then it's permissible earlier. Which by
the way there's a certain logical power to that, that the bringing
of the קורבן korban makes it permissible sooner as opposed to the
other approach where the bringing of the קורבן, korban, the presence of
the קורבן korban made you have to wait more. Here the bringing
of the קורבן korban makes it permissible sooner. So as Moshe said...
So וכי סבר לה כוותיה? vechi savar leh kavatei? Does he really
hold like him? והא מיפלג פליג עליה? veha miflag palig alei? He
argues on him! דתניא, detanya, we taught, or דתנן, detnan, we taught
in the משנה, Mishnah, משחרב בית המקדש, mishecharav Beit Hamikdash, התקין רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי hitkin Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai שיהא יום הנף כולו
אסור. sheyehi yom hanef kulo asur. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai said the day of waving should be totally forbidden. To
the different משנה, Mishnah, not ours. ואמר רבי יהודה, ve'amar Rabi Yehuda,
and in that משנה, Mishnah, רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda responded to him.
Now he didn't really respond to him because he didn't live in
the same generation. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was
at the time of the חורבן. churban. רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda was
a student of רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, so he's like in the
year 150, 170, if I'm not mistaken. But רש"י Rashi says he's
like responding to his position. So רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda responded to
this position and said, for what do you mean, it's rabbinically forbidden
the whole day, it's a תקנה takkanah to be forbidden the whole
day. והלא מן התורה הוא אסור? vehalo min Hatorah hu asur? Biblically
it's forbidden the whole day if you don't have an עומר. omer.
דכתיב, dechsiv, עד עצם היום הזה, ad etzem hayom hazeh, עד עיצומו
של יום, ad itzumo shel yom, until the very day itself has
passed. So the גמרא Gemara says no, רבי יהודה הוא דקא טעי.
Rabi Yehuda hu de-katai. רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda misunderstood what רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was saying. הוא סבר מדבנן. hu
savar mi-derabbanan. He thought רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
was saying rabbinically it's forbidden the whole day now that there's no
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash קאמר. ka-amar. ולאו היא, velav hi, that's not
what he meant. מדאורייתא קאמר. mi-d'oreisa ka-amar. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai meant now that there's no בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
biblically it's forbidden the whole day. So the גמרא Gemara says והתקין
קאמר? ve-hitkin ka-amar? But it says רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai established an edict, meaning established a new position. So it
sounds like it is rabbinic if it's not... it doesn't sound like
it's a biblical idea that it's forbidden the whole day. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, מאי התקין? mai hitkin? What does התקין hitkin
mean? דרש והתקין. darash vehitkin. It means he expounded the new law
and established the practice. But he established a practice that he believed
was a biblical practice. There had been a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
so nobody ever needed to know what was the הלכה halakhah if
there isn't a קרבן. korban. Then the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash was
destroyed. So he expounded to the masses and taught them that now
that there's no בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, it's forbidden the whole day.
But he wasn't teaching them a new rabbinic edict, he was teaching
them what the הלכה halakhah is. The הלכה halakhah is without a
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash it's forbidden the whole day. So that leaves
that position, although it's a stretch on the word התקין, hitkin, makes
more... at least makes a certain amount of sense. It makes sense
A, that the קרבן korban makes it permissible sooner rather than later,
and it makes sense that you don't have to create some crazy
scenario like the גמרא Gemara did that we're afraid the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash will be built דווקא davka the night before and that'll
lead to a problem, okay, because it's hard to understand what this
issue is, what would be this concern that he would have to
say don't eat it the whole day. And according to this, it's
a biblical הלכה halakhah rather than a rabbinic
concern. Okay, we'll do one more משנה. Mishnah. יום טוב ראשון שחל
להיות בשבת. yom tov rishon she-chal lihyos be-Shabbos.
Now, so we mentioned that the first day is biblical everywhere, the
remaining seven days are only in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Now
we're going to talk about what happens on... will happen on the
first day that falls out on שבת. Shabbos. Now we know we
don't take the לולב lulav on the first day that falls out
on שבת. Shabbos. But in the משנה, Mishnah, both this משנה Mishnah
and the next... and the first opening משנה Mishnah of the next
פרק perek will say that they took the לולב lulav when it
fell out on שבת, Shabbos, okay?
What?
That's what it should be. Well, that's what it was. That used
to be that they would take the לולב lulav when first day...
when חול המועד chol hamoed fell out on שבת Shabbos they would
not because that would only be rabbinic or even in the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash they wouldn't do it because it would only be
biblical in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, but on the first day
which is biblical everywhere, they would take the לולב lulav even when
it fell out on שבת. Shabbos. So let's read that. What?
Too hard to carry?
No, let's see what they did. Carry, but you would take the
לולב. lulav. Let's see what they did. יום טוב ראשון של חג
שחל להיות בשבת. yom tov rishon shel chag she-chal lihyos be-Shabbos. The
first day of יום טוב Yom Tov falls out on שבת. Shabbos.
כל המוליכין את לולביהם לבית הכנסת, kol hamolichen es lulaveihem le-veit haknesses,
everybody would bring their לולב lulav to the synagogue. Again, fitting into
the previous משנה Mishnah that takes it for granted that the primary
place in which you're taking the לולב lulav is in synagogue during
the הלל, Hallel, right? Remember just the previous discussion, just where do
you do the נענועים? nanuim? What if you came home and you
didn't have a לולב lulav in your hand? Oh, you can take
it at home. But the basic assumption is you're taking the לולב
lulav in שול shul at הלל. Hallel. So what would you do
if it's falling out on שבת? Shabbos? You can't carry it to
שול shul on שבת. Shabbos. So you would go ahead and you'd
prepare ahead of
time. כל המוליכין את לולביהם לבית הכנסת, kol hamolichen es lulaveihem le-veit
haknesses, on ערב שבת erev Shabbos everybody would prepare and bring their
לולב lulav to שול. shul. למחרת, lemacharas, the next day, שבת Shabbos
morning, משכימין ובאין, mashkimin u-va'in, everybody would wake up early. We'll see
why you want to be early. כל אחד ואחד מכיר שלו ונוטל
לו, kol echad ve-echad makir shelo ve-notel lo, because you would want
to not have to go ahead and fight and deal with the
crowds, so the early bird gets the worm and I guess the
early congregant gets the לולב. lulav. So you would go ahead and
you'd recognize your לולב, lulav, maybe you'd have a little... you'd have
it in a container with your name on it and you'd take
it. מפני שאמרו חכמים, mipnei she'amru chachamim, because the sages said, אין
אדם יוצא ידי חובתו ביום טוב ראשון בלולבו של חבירו. ein adam
yotzei yedei chovaso be-yom tov rishon be-lulavo shel chaveiro. You can't fulfill
your obligation with your friend's לולב. lulav. So therefore it's in שול
shul because you had it prepared from before שבת Shabbos and you
have to recognize yours because you're only יוצא yotzei with yours. ובשאר
ימי החג, uvish'ar yemai hachag, and the other days of the holiday,
אדם יוצא ידי חובתו בלולבו של חבירו, adam yotzei yedei chovaso be-lulavo
shel chaveiro, you can use your friend's לולב. lulav. Fine. But not
on this day. So this day you had to identify yours and
it was already in שול, shul, you weren't holding onto it from
ahead of time. רבי יוסי Rabi Yose Rabbi Yosi says, יום טוב
ראשון של חג שחל להיות בשבת ושכח והוציא את הלולב לרשות הרבים,
Yom Tov rishon shel chag shechal lihyot beShabbos veshachach vehotzi es halulav
lerashus harabim, let’s say you forgot, you didn’t leave your לולב lulav
in שול. shul. It was the first day יום טוב, Yom Tov,
it happened on שבת. Shabbos. Again, we’re assuming people take the לולב
lulav on the first on the first day יום טוב, Yom Tov,
even on שבת. Shabbos. So you’re taking your לולב, lulav, but you
didn’t bring it to שול shul ahead of time and you accidentally
walked out of your house with it. You gotta go to שול
shul in the morning, so you take your לולב lulav off the
table and you walk out of your house and then you realize,
oh my gosh, it’s שבת Shabbos and I just carried on שבת
Shabbos and I have my לולב lulav in my hand. So what’s
the הלכה? halacha? פטור, Patur, because he brought it out with permission.
You’re not allowed to do it, but you’re exempt from a קרבן
korban because you took it out with permission. This is Rabbi Yosi’s
general position, which is actually it’s also the debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua of טועה בדבר מצוה. toeh
bidvar mitzvah. You were doing a מצוה mitzvah and you accidentally, not
intentionally, accidentally did an עבירה aveira in the context of doing the
מצוה. mitzvah. And often it relates to שבת. Shabbos. You know you
have to perform a ברית מילה, bris milah, you’re a מוהל, mohel,
it’s the eighth day, and accidentally you give a מילה milah to
the wrong baby. Okay, you know you’re supposed to take a לולב
lulav and it’s יום טוב Yom Tov on שבת Shabbos and this
was at a time when they would take the לולב lulav on
יום טוב Yom Tov when it fell out on שבת. Shabbos. But
you’re doing the מצוה mitzvah of taking לולב, lulav, but you accidentally
walk out of your house. You didn’t leave it in the שול
shul ahead of time. So you’re being טועה בדבר מצוה. toeh bidvar
mitzvah. That exempts you from bringing a קרבן. korban. Obviously, you’re not
allowed to do this חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, but if you accidentally
did, the fact that you were עוסק במצוה oseik bemitzvah exempts you
from the obligation of the קרבן. korban. Yes.
Didn’t we see in עירובין Eiruvin they were mentioning that there was
an עירוב eiruv in ירושלים Yerushalayim back in? Who says?
Where in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Rabbi Yosi was in לוד. Lod.
Yeah, I’m talking about the when they were bringing them in the
temple.
Oh, you mean why they have to bring it. That’s a good
question. If you’re in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, why would you have to bring
it to the temple? You could put it anywhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Yeah, but this isn’t necessarily ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We’ll talk about that in
the next משנה. mishnah. This is בית הכנסת. beis haknesses. So this
would be not necessarily assuming you have a walled city. Okay, מנא
הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where do you get this idea from?
The difference between the first day and the rest of, excuse
me, that there’s a מצוה mitzvah to take it on the first
day and it has to be yours, this issue of ownership, something
we’ve said before. Where do you get this from? דתנו רבנן, Detanu
rabanan, we taught: ולקחתם, Ulekachtem, you shall take, שתהא לקיחה ביד כל
אחד ואחד, shetehei lekicha beyad kol echad ve’echad, every individual has to
take. As opposed to meaning one person takes for everyone. Now, this
actually is interesting and it’s important to know in terms of hermeneutics
the difference between the singular language and the plural language. If I
said ולקחת ulekachta as opposed to ולקחתם, ulekachtem, singular or plural, you
might think ולקחת ulekachta means you as an individual have to take.
ולקחתם Ulekachtem maybe means you as a community and maybe one person
could take for everybody. But basically it’s the exact opposite. The גמרא,
Gemara,
for example, think about the מצוה mitzvah of counting. There’s two מצוות
mitzvos of counting in the תורה. Torah. One מצוה mitzvah says וספרתם
לכם ממחרת השבת מיום הביאכם את עומר התנופה שבע שבתות תמימות תהיינה,
Usefartem lachem mimacharas haShabbos miyom havi’achem es omer hatenufo sheva shabbasos temimos
tiheiyena, counting the עומר, omer, וספרתם usefartem בלשון רבים. bilshon rabim. And
the other one says וספרת לך שבע שבתות שנים שבע שנים שבע
פעמים, Vesafarta lecha sheva shabbasos shanim sheva shanim sheva pe’amim, counting the
years for the יובל. Yovel. וספרת לך, Vesafarta lecha, singular. Which one
do we do as an individual obligation? Counting the עומר. omer. Which
one is only an obligation on בית דין? beis din? Counting the
יובל. Yovel. So actually the plural language means you, meaning all of
you guys. It’s in the plural, every single one of you, all
you guys, all you people, everyone of you. That’s the plural language,
וספרתם לכם. usefartem lachem. וספרת לך Vesafarta lecha in the singular means
the entirety of you as one corporate entity. I’m speaking to the
whole room and I’m saying you in the singular meaning you as
one corporate entity. So therefore it’s done by the בית דין beis
din for everyone else. That’s the counting of the יובל. Yovel. As
opposed to the plural language which means all of you as individuals.
So that’s what the גמרא Gemara says. If it had said ולקחת
לך, ulekachta lecha, one person could take the לולב lulav for everyone.
But ולקחתם לכם ulekachtem lachem means all of you as individuals have
to take it. So that’s the first point of שתהא לקיחה ביד
כל אחד ואחד. shetehei lekicha beyad kol echad ve’echad. Every individual has
to take a לולב. lulav. לכם, Lachem, you, משלכם, mishelachem, it has
to belong to you. והוציא את השאול ואת הגזול, Vehotzi es hashaul
ve’es hagazul, which excludes a borrowed or stolen לולב lulav and אתרוג.
esrog. מכאן אמרו חכמים, Mikan amru chachamim, here the rabbis said: אין
אדם יוצא ידי חובתו ביום טוב הראשון של חג בלולבו של חבירו,
Ein adam yotze yedei chovaso beYom Tov harishon shel chag belulavo shel
chaveiro, you don’t fulfill your obligation on the first day of the
holiday with your friend’s לולב lulav even if it’s borrowed, certainly not
if it’s stolen. And that’s ביום הראשון, beYom harishon, that’s only on
day one. אלא אם כן נתנו לו במתנה, Ela im ken nesano
lo bematana,
unless it’s given as a gift. ומעשה, Umaaseh, and then there’s a
story: רבן גמליאל ורבי יהושע ורבי אלעזר בן עזריה ורבי עקיבא, Rabban
Gamliel veRabbi Yehoshua veRabbi Elazar ben Azarya veRabbi Akiva, all these great
rabbis, שהיו באין בספינה, shehayu ba’in besfina, they were traveling on a
ship. There’s actually interesting speculation about where they were traveling because there
was a certain around that time there was an intercession of rabbis
with the Roman government. Some want to associate it with that. Anyway,
ולא היה לולב אלא לרבן גמליאל בלבד, velo haya lulav ela leRabban
Gamliel bilvad, and Rabban Gamliel was the only one who had brought
a לולב lulav with him, לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog it means
and the whole thing. שלקחו באלף זוז. Shelekacho be’elef zuz. You see,
spending an insane amount of money, an obscene amount of money, is
not a new thing on the idea of לולב lulav and
אתרוג. esrog. He spent
a
thousand זוז. zuz. Maybe, maybe... Who else is selling לולבים ואתרוגים lulavim
u-etrogim on a ship? The one guy
who had the לולב ואתרוג lulav ve-etrog was selling it for a
thousand זוז. zuz. Anyway, נטלו רבן גמליאל ויצא בו. natlo Rabban Gamliel
ve-yatza bo. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel took it and was
יצא. yotze. ונתנו לרבי יהושע במתנה. ve-nasno le-Rabbi Yehoshua be-matana. He didn't
lend it to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua because that wouldn't be יצא.
yotze. He gave it to him as a gift. נטלו רבי יהושע
ויצא בו. natlo Rabbi Yehoshua ve-yatza bo. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua took
it and was יצא, yotze, and then he turned around
and ונתנו לרבי אלעזר בן עזריה במתנה. ve-nasno le-Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya
be-matana. Then he turned around, so it is we're right now, right,
it's פורים Purim and it's going to be שלח מנות, Shalach Manos,
so it is already the idea of regifting, right, regifting was already
thought of that way before us. Okay, so he regifted it to
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, ויצא בו. ve-yatza bo. ונתנו לרבי עקיבא במתנה.
ve-nasno le-Rabbi Akiva be-matana. And then רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya gave it as a gift to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
נטלו רבי עקיבא ויצא בו. natla Rabbi Akiva ve-yatza bo. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva took it and was יצא, yotze, but they all gave
it as gifts, not as a loan. והחזירו לרבן גמליאל. ve-hechziro le-Rabban
Gamliel. And then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva gave it back to רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel because you would expect רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would
like to have his thousand dollar לולב ואתרוג lulav ve-etrog back. So
the גמרא Gemara says, למה לי למימר החזירו? lama li le-meimar hechziro?
Why do you have to tell me he returned them? I mean
that was an interesting side note but it's not halachically significant, is
it? Yes, it is. אגב אורחא קמשמע לן, agav orcha kamashma lan,
it's telling us something in passing. מתנה על מנת להחזיר שמה מתנה.
matana al menat le-hachzir shema matana. It
wasn't just רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva out of the kindness of his
heart gave it back. We're going to assume that the gift was
originally given on the condition that eventually it gets back to רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. And therefore because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel wanted his
thousand dollar לולב lulav back. So you could say if you give
me a gift on the condition that I give it back, it's
not a gift, it's a loan, and maybe I'm not יצא, yotze,
right? No, even if it's on that condition, it still is considered
a gift. You have to fulfill the condition, but it is a
status of a gift and therefore you are taking something that right
now is yours and you are יצא. yotze. כי הא דאמר רבא,
ki ha
de-amar Rava, like what רבא Rava
said, הילך לך אתרוג זה על מנת שתחזירהו לי. helach lecha esrog
ze al menat she-tachzirehu li.
Here's this אתרוג esrog on the condition that you give it back
to me. נטלו ויצא בו, natlo ve-yatza bo, you take it and
you're יצא yotze because now it's yours. It can't be a loan,
it has to be yours. החזירו יצא. hechziro yatza.
If you returned it, you fulfilled your obligation because you've satisfied this
condition.
לא החזירו לא יצא. lo hechziro lo yatza. You did not fulfill
your obligation. Why? Because if you didn't return it, then if the
whole gift was a conditional gift and you didn't return it, it
turns out that it was never a gift. So then when you
were taking it, it was stolen, right? It was only given to
you as a gift on the condition that eventually you would return
it. By the way, we see from the end of this story
that at least in רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel case, the condition wasn't
that the first person returned it. The condition was that it be
returned in the end. Whoever in the end has it, eventually it
be returned, that at least was רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel condition. But
that's an idea that you would have said, ah come on, give
me a break, if that's what's going on, it's a loan, it's
not a gift. And the חידוש chiddush of רבא, Rava, which is
being read into this story, is that no, it actually does constitute
an actual gift even though there is a condition. Now there's other
גמרות Gemaros that raise questions to what degree is it fully considered
a gift or not that תוספות Tosfos tries to work out, but
this generally is our assumption. Michael asked the question about a case
of קידושין, Kiddushin, other types of cases, all those cases get looked
at. But this is this is at least our application here and
this is very relevant להלכה le-halacha because somebody doesn't have a לולב
ואתרוג lulav ve-etrog and they want to borrow it on the first
day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, so you can just give it
as a gift without saying here's a gift על מנת להחזיר al
menat le-hachzir on the condition because hopefully people will sort of understand
like was Tal's פשט pshat of the story of רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, but also you can say it's מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana
al menat le-hachzir and therefore you know that you're going to be
יצא. yotze. I'll take the question in a second, I just want
to say two points about תוספות. Tosfos. If you look at תוספות,
Tosfos, it makes two interesting relevant applications. תוספות Tosfos says like this,
ובאתרוג של
שותפין, uve-esrog she-shutfim, the top תוספות, Tosfos, he says ובאתרוג של שותפין
נמי לא
נפיק. uve-esrog she-shutfim nami lo nafik. If it was a partnership אתרוג,
esrog, you're also not יצא. yotze. You have to be the sole
owner. He says, and then like skipping like four lines down, he
says, and four like five lines down at the word אלא, ela,
he says, ומה שנהגו הקהל לקנות אתרוג בשותפות. u-ma she-nahagu ha-kahal liknot
etrog be-shutfut. This is what they used to do in Europe. They
would buy a לולב ואתרוג lulav ve-etrog as a everybody would chip
it together and they would all buy it with communal funds because
nobody could afford one by themselves. So he says, how does that
work if it's owned communally you're not יצא, yotze, you have to
own it privately. So מלמדין אותן שיהיו כולם נותנים כל אחד ואחד
חלקו לחבירו על מנת
להחזיר. melamdin otan she-yehu kulam notnim kol echad ve-echad chelko le-chavero al
menat le-hachzir. The implicit stipulation is we own this communally and when
it's your turn to take it, we're everybody else is giving it
to you as a מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matana al menat le-hachzir.
And then you're done and then you give it to Michael and
then everybody gives it to him as a מתנה על מנת להחזיר
matana al menat le-hachzir and so on and so forth. So תוספות
Tosfos says this the reality was it was communal, but we have
to assume there was some implicit or explicit stipulation that meant that
people would own it individually when it was their turn. This plays
out by the way when you take on a שול shul טלית.
tallis. Do you make a ברכה bracha or not? Because you don't
make a ברכה bracha on a borrowed טלית tallis and you know
and how does it play out? This similar idea well the assumption
is that if you take take it and you want to use
it to be יוצא yotzei that the שול shul gives it to
you as like a מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana al menas lehachzir
or something so that you can make the
ברכה. brachah. Anyway plays out interestingly in similar types of scenarios. Talking
about קידושין, kiddushin, there used to be a ring, you ever go
to the Jewish museums and you'll see these very like big rings
like they have like towers built on them. Anyway they were used
as communal wedding rings. How do you use it since you have
to own the ring that you're giving? It was a similar type
of a thing. It was owned by the community, but when it
was your turn to use it it became yours. So that's number
one, just sort of reflects that reality. I'll just read the rest
of תוספות, Tosafos, he says, ויש לסמוך דכיון דקנו על מנת לצאת
בו, Veyeish lismoch d'keivan d'kanu al menas latzes bo, since you purchased
it for the purpose of everybody being יוצא, yotzei, אף על גב
שלא פירשו, af al gav shelo peirshu, even though they didn't explicitly
say when each person's turn it would be a gift to that
person, סתמא דמילתא כאילו פירשו
דמי. stama d'milsa k'ilu peirshu dami. It's assumed to be that that
was the implicit understanding and intent that were operating with that each
person gets it when it's their turn. That being said, although תוספות
Tosafos here just said we can sort of make it an implicit
intent, the next תוספות Tosafos of here's your אתרוג esrog on the
condition you return it to me has a whole problem because there's
other גמרות Gemoras that say that when you make stipulations, if you
do something on the condition of X, that you have to satisfy
a lot of technical conditions to make it a binding
stipulation, like it's learned out from the what's called תנאי בני גד
ובני ראובן, tnai b'nei gad u'v'nei re'uven, the way when משה Moshe
said well if you go in and you fight with your brethren
then you can come back and inherit the land on עבר הירדן,
eiver hayarden, and it had all of these ways first he said
if this then that and if not then
not, a yes clause and a no clause, and first he said
the condition and then he said the action, and there's all these
requirements in order to make binding stipulations. And the question is when
you need to satisfy those requirements or not. תוספות Tosafos so very
often we say you don't really need to do it as long
as it's implicitly your understanding and so on. Anyway, the next תוספות
Tosafos suggests that maybe you have to make all those stipulations. If
you look at just the beginning of the next תוספות, Tosafos, הילכך
הקנהו זה במתנה, hilkach hikneihu zeh b'matana, he says, בשום מקום אין
מדקדק הש"ס לשונו להקדים תנאי למעשה ותנאי כפול והן קודם ללאו, beshum
makom ein medakdeik ha-shas l'shono l'hakdim tnai l'maaseh u'tnai kaful v'hein kodem
l'lav,
those are all the technical requirements of making conditions, that you have
to first say the condition before the action, you have to double
the condition, you have to say the yes clause before the no
clause. אף על גב דבהכי מיירי, af al gav d'behachi mairi, that
you would have to do all of that, אלא שמקצר בלשונו, ella
she-mekatzer bi-lshono, but it's just not going into that detail. So this
תוספות Tosafos says that yes, if you want to give something מתנה
על מנת להחזיר, matana al menas lehachzir, you have to make sure
you satisfy all of the technical conditions of making stipulations. Other ראשונים
Rishonim and other times תוספות Tosafos says you don't have to satisfy
all those conditions, that sometimes those can just be assumed to be
your intention. And that's by the way what we see in the
previous תוספות, Tosafos, right? They bought this אתרוג esrog in partnership and
he says even without saying anything you can just assume that they
wanted to operate with a certain type of parameters. So that's basically
this idea of מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana al menas lehachzir which
as I said plays out really on סוכות Succos when you lend
people, lend, give them מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana al menas lehachzir
on the first day, and can play out in other ways about
communal things that are shared, but that in order to be יוצא
yotzei you actually have to have complete ownership over it. Yes, Michael?
Wait, there is a ישיוב הקושיא yishuv hakushya because it can't be
קונה koneh and not מקנה? makne? Yeah, we'll discuss that later about
whether מתנה על מנת להחזיר matana al menas lehachzir just means the
act of giving it back or does it actually mean being מקנה
makne it back and so on and whatever, we'll see that later.
גמרא Gemara discusses the ישיוב הקושיא. yishuv hakushya. And the idea that
טלית, tallis, the communal טלית tallis in
a שול, shul, so that's a choice you're making because like sometimes
like for סליחות Selichos
or if you're just getting an עליה aliyah and you put on
the שול'ס shul's טלית tallis or whatever or you're getting up to
דאבנינג davening and you put on the שול'ס shul's טלית, tallis, most
people don't make a ברכה. brachah. They just put it on, I
mean, I've seen people, because you don't have to take the ownership
over it. That's correct.
Any problems with transferring ownership on יום
טוב? Yom Tov?
Clearly not. You're
allowed to be מקנה makne things that are לצורך שבת l'tzorech Shabbos
and לצורך יום טוב. l'tzorech Yom Tov. So there's normally a practice,
for example, I'm going to your house and I'm going to
bring you over a bottle of wine or something, so if I'm
real פרום frum I give it to somebody else and have them
be קונה koneh for you so you don't have to be קונה
koneh on שבת. Shabbos. But the reality is that if what I'm
giving you is something that you can use on שבת, Shabbos, then
I'm allowed to be מקנה makneh you on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. למה לי למימר שקנאו
באלף זוז?
Lama li l'meimar
she-knahu b'elef zuz? Why put, very colorful story, but why do you
have to point out that little detail that he spent a thousand
dollars on it? So the גמרא Gemara says להודיעך כמה מצות חביבות
עליהן, l'hodiecha kama mitzvos chavivos aleihen,
to tell you how dear the mitzvos were to them and how
much money they were willing to spend just to be יוצא yotzei
לולב lulav and אתרוג. esrog. אמר ליה מר בר אמימר לרב אשי,
Amar lei Mar bar Ameimar l'Rav Ashi, אבא צלויי קמצלי ביה, abba
tzuluyei ka-matzlei bei, my father אמימר, Ameimar, when
he would be holding onto his לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog when
he was דאבנינג. davening. מתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on that, לא
יאחז אדם תפילין בידו וספר תורה בחיקו ויתפלל, lo yochez adam tefillin
b'yado v'sefer torah b'cheiko v'yispalleil,
a person should not be holding תפילין tefillin in his hand meaning
not. wrapped on his arm but holding them in the palm of
his hand or a ספר תורה sefer Torah in his chest and
דאוון daven because you'll be distracted, you'll have to focus on holding
on to them and you won't be focused on your דאווענינג davening
or the reverse, if you focus on your דאווענינג, davening, then you'll
let them drop. אבל לא ישתין בהם, Aval lo yashtin bahem, it's
a separate point, you should not be urinating while you're holding on
to your תפילין tefillin and ספר תורה. sefer Torah. ולא יישן בהם
V'lo yishan bahem and you shouldn't be sleeping, not only when the
תפילין tefillin is wrapped on your arm but even if you're just
holding it in your hand. לא שינת קבע ולא שינת עראי, Lo
shinat keva v'lo shinat arai, not a permanent or temporary sleep because
if you fall asleep holding on to the תפילין tefillin or ספר
תורה, sefer Torah, you'll drop them. ואמר שמואל, V'amar Shmuel, and it's
not just limited by the way, you'll say, well maybe that's תפילין
tefillin and ספר תורה. sefer Torah. No, it's not limited to that.
שמואל Shmuel also says סכין וקערה, sakin v'kaara,
a knife or a plate, a dish, וכיכר ומעות v'kikar u'maot
or bread or money, הרי אלו כיוצא בהם harei elu k'yozei bahem
and the same issue, all these are things that you're afraid you're
going to drop even though they're not sanctified objects. You don't want
to drop your knife on your foot, you don't want to drop
a plate it'll break, right? You don't want to drop bread it'll
get dirty. So you see if you're afraid you'll drop something you
can't hold it while you're דאווענינג. davening. So how can you hold
a לולב lulav while you're דאווענינג? davening? So the גמרא Gemara says
התם לאו מצוה נינהו וטרדי. Hatam lav mitzvah ninhu v'tardi. There,
you're not doing a מצוה mitzvah by taking by holding on to
these things and therefore you're distracted. הכא מצוה נינהו ולא טרדי. Hacha
mitzvah ninhu v'lo tardi. Here you're doing a מצוה mitzvah and you're
not distracted, which is pretty funny, although you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah,
why does it mean you're not distracted? You still don't want to
drop your לולב lulav and אתרוג. esrog. What makes you not distracted?
So if you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says
like this, לאו מצוה נינהו lav mitzvah ninhu about eight lines from
the bottom לאוחזן. l'ochzan. It's not a מצוה mitzvah to hold them
all these other things, והוו להו למשא v'havu lehu l'masa
and therefore psychologically it's like a burden, it's a distraction. ואיכא טרדת
משאן וכבד עליו משאן ומשמרתן, V'ika tirdat masaan v'kaved alav masaan u'mishmartan,
therefore you're distracted because it is literally the burden is heavy but
it's also like metaphoric, right, psychologically it's a heavy burden, ugh, I
gotta be paying attention to holding on to this stuff. הכא נטילתה
ולקיחתה מצוה היא, Hacha netilata u'lekichata mitzvah hi, the
fact that you're taking it, your holding on to it is a
מצוה, mitzvah, ומתוך שחביבה מצוה עליו, u'mitech shechaviva mitzvah alav, you're like
you're thrilled to be doing this מצוה, mitzvah, אין משא שמירתן כבד
עליו ולא טרדי, ein masa shamirtan kaved alav v'lo tardi, you don't
psychologically it's not a burden and therefore it's not distracting to you,
which is again pretty funny, you gotta be careful not to drop
it but somehow psychologically if you're like thrilled to be doing it
then it actually somehow is not seen as a concern that holding
on to it will serve as a source of distraction. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניא, Tanya, we turn the
ברייתא, baraita, רבי אלעזר בר צדוק אומר כך היה מנהגן של אנשי
ירושלים, Rabbi Elazar Bar Tzadok omer kach haya minhagan shel anshei Yerushalayim,
this was the practice of the people of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אדם יוצא
מביתו ולולבו בידו, adam yotzei mibeito v'lulavo beyado,
you'd walk out of your house you'd be holding on to your
לולב, lulav, הולך לבית הכנסת ולולבו בידו, holech l'veit haknesset v'lulavo beyado,
you go to the שול shul holding on to your לולב, lulav,
קורא קריאת שמע ומתפלל ולולבו בידו, korei krias shema u'mitpaleil v'lulavo beyado,
even when you're דאווענינג, davening, even when you're saying שמע Shema holding
on to your לולב, lulav, קורא בתורה
ונושא כפיו מניחו על גבי קרקע, korei baTorah v'nosei kapav manicho al
gabei karka, now when you got an עליה aliyah or when you're
a כהן kohen and you did דוכן, duchening, then you would put
it on the ground. דוכן Duchening obviously you need your hands free
but even when you're getting an עליה aliyah
you have to roll the תורה Torah open and close, right, you're
not just getting an עליה aliyah you're reading from it so you're
closing it and opening it, so you need your hands free. הולך
לבקר חולים ולנחם אבלים ולולבו בידו, holech l'vaker cholim u'lenachem avelim v'lulavo
beyado, now you're done דאווענינג davening in שול, shul, what are you
going to spend the rest of your day doing on סוכות? Sukkos?
You're going to do מצוות mitzvos the rest of the day. So
you're going to visit the sick and to console the mourners, לולבו
בידו, lulavo beyado, you come with your לולב, lulav, you see this
is the first sort of source of חב״ד, Chabad, you walk into
the hospital, did you take לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog yet? Okay
fine, anyway. נכנס לבית המדרש משגר לולבו ביד בנו ביד עבדו ביד
שלוחו, nichnas l'veit hamidrash meshager lulavo beyad beno beyad avdo beyad shlucho,
then you send it home. Why do you send it home? Because
now you're going to spend the rest of the day in the
בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, so you don't want to leave it on
the floor because that's not respectful. So then you get one of
your servant or your kid to bring it home. Why didn't you
hold it with you? Because when you're learning then actually it is
a distraction, which is interesting, when you're דאווענינג davening not but when
you're learning it is. מאי קמשמע לן, Mai kamashma lan, so anyway
what does all this teach? להודיעך כמה היו זריזין במצות, l'hodiacha kama
hayu zerizin bemitzvot, how zealous or they were with the מצוה. mitzvah.
Now part of the idea here is not just you're holding on
to it, what wouldn't for example say we never see like you
should hold on to your שופר shofar for the whole day of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah or go around all of חנוכה Chanukah holding
on to like your חנוכיה, channukiah, because here the holding on is
actually the act of the מצוה, mitzvah, ולקחתם לכם, u'lekachtem lachem, so
you're just continuing to do the act of the מצוה mitzvah the
whole day. Even though you're יוצא yotzei in that first moment, your
holding on to it is the continuation of the מצוה mitzvah throughout
the day. So let's read a little bit more, we have a
little more time, let's see if we can get to the משנה.
Mishnah. רבי יוסי אומר יום טוב, Rabbi Yosi omer yom tov, now
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that if you accidentally walk out of
the house on the, again this was assuming you would take it
on יום טוב Yom Tov that was on שבת Shabbos and you
accidentally walked out of the house on יום טוב Yom Tov שבת,
Shabbos, you would not be, you would be exempt from a sin
offering because you were doing a מצוה. mitzvah. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
said אביי, Abaye, לא שנו אלא שלא יצא בו. lo shanu ela
shelo yatza bo. It's only true that you are exempt from your
sin offering if you have not yet been יוצא, yotze, so you're
still in the process of doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, אבל יצא
בו, aval yatza bo, if you already יוצא yotze when you took
the לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog at home and then you stepped
out of the house, well that was the question, חייב, chayav, then
you are חייב chayav a sin offering because you're no longer in
the process of doing a מצוה. mitzvah. We just learned before you
could still be doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but once you've been יוצא
yotze already, you're like no longer distracted by the מצוה, mitzvah, involved
in the מצוה, mitzvah, once you're already יוצא yotze it's behind you
and you cannot, and the fact that you're still carrying it and
still doing a מצוה mitzvah does not exempt you. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well what's the scenario then? How is it ever possible
you weren't יוצא yotze yet? המדאגבה נפיק בה, ha mi-de-agbeha nefik be,
as soon as you picked it up to step out of the
house you were already יוצא. yotze. So what do you mean? What's
the scenario you weren't יוצא yotze yet? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
so אביי Abaye says, כשהפכו, keshehaphacho,
you turned it upside down. If you're carrying it like we discussed
earlier, you know, you turn it upside down before making the ברכה,
bracha, so you specifically picked it up in a way not to
be יוצא yotze because you're going to bring it to שול, shul,
you want to wait until you get to שול shul to make
the ברכה, bracha, so you picked it up upside down so you
haven't been יוצא yotze yet. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says,
and you only are יוצא yotze when it's right-side up, as we'll
see later. רבא Rava says, אפילו תימא שלא הפכו, afilu teima shelo
hafacho, even if you didn't turn it upside down, הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון שהוציאו בכלי, hacha bemai askinan kegon shehotzio bikli,
you're carrying it out in a לולב lulav holder and you're not
יוצא yotze because you're not holding it directly. The גמרא Gemara says,
אהא רבא הוא דאמר רבא, aha Rava hu d'amar Rava, רבא Rava
himself was the one who said it, לקיחה על ידי דבר אחר
שמה לקיחה, lekicha al yedei davar acher shema lekicha, if you take
it by holding it on with a handle, it's considered taking, even
if you didn't directly hold it, through another thing is considered taking.
So even if you're holding it in a vessel isn't it like
taking? So the גמרא Gemara says, הני מילי דרך כבוד, hani mili
derech kavod,
that's only if it's a respectful way of taking, אבל דרך בזיון,
aval derech bizayon,
a disgracing way of taking, לא אמר, lo amar, he would not
say no, he would not say that.
So now the question is what makes it disgraceful? Would you really
take it out in a disgraceful, I mean there's a huge gap
between כבוד kavod and בזיון, bizayon, there's everything in the middle which
is neutral, right? When we take it out in our לולב lulav
holders, I wouldn't say it's בזיון, bizayon, I wouldn't necessarily say it's
כבוד, kavod, it's just a convenient way of taking. So with רש"י
Rashi it sounds more like it has to be כבוד kavod in
order to be considered like as an act of taking. רש"י Rashi
says if you were holding on to it with like a nice
silk handkerchief or something and you're using that as a handle to
hold it, then it's considered like an act of taking. But if
you're holding it in רש"י Rashi just says a כלי, kli, a
vessel, it's not. A vessel isn't בזיון bizayon but it's not כבוד.
kavod. So in order for it to be an indirect taking to
count as a taking, it has to be something that is seen
as a respectful way of doing it. So this is actually a
very relevant question because when we learned רבא Rava earlier, I think
it was you who asked, right, what so meaning so what about
every time I walk out of my house, I got my אתרוג
esrog in my nice אתרוג esrog box, which is right-side up, the
אתרוג, esrog, and I got my לולב lulav in my לולב lulav
holder, which is right-side up, and why isn't it לקיחה על ידי
דבר אחר? lekicha al yedei davar acher? Why aren't I יוצא? yotze?
Why can I make the ברכה bracha when I get to שול?
shul? Now we do say even if you were יוצא yotze you
can still make the ברכה bracha before you did the נענועים, nanuim,
we do hold like רבא. Rava. But it does seem that that
is considered not to be לקיחה דרך כבוד. lekicha derech kavod. Just
have my נענועים? nanuim? Well, the גמרא Gemara didn't say, well you
could, but you normally don't, you just take it, right, you just
walk out of your house with it. So why, so anyway, so
it does seem that the לקיחה דרך כבוד lekicha derech kavod is
a narrow, is defined narrowly and in most cases would not be
that scenario. Now the question that Michael just said is why didn't
the גמרא Gemara give the answer about כוונה? kavana? Why did the
גמרא Gemara just say you didn't have כוונה? kavana? Well, there's a
debate whether מצוות צריכות כוונה, mitzvot tzerichot kavana, lack of כוונה kavana
you still might be יוצא. yotze. Well then תוספות, Tosafot, well why
didn't it say you had negative כוונה, kavana, you had כוונה kavana
not to be יוצא? yotze? So maybe in theory it could have
said that but again that's also like harder to detect and to
the obvious and therefore, and but that is always a possibility. Let's
read a little bit further. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, אמר האי רבי יוסי, amar hai
Rabbi Yose, said רב הונא, Rav Huna, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who
said you're exempt, he used to say, עולת העוף שנמצא בין האגפיים,
olat ha-of shenimtza bein ha-gapayim, if you find a bird עולה ola
between, רש"י Rashi says, האגפיים ha-gapayim just means other dead birds by
the foot of the מזבח, mizbeach, וכסבור חטאת העוף היא, vekasavar chatat
ha-of hi, and you assume
it's a bird brought as a חטאת. chatat. Now you're a כהן,
Kohen, your מצוה mitzvah is to eat the חטאת chatat bird, but
the עולה ola birds have to be burnt. Now usually the עולה
ola birds were in a different corner of the מזבח, mizbeach, on
the floor of the מזבח, mizbeach, but it happened to be that
because there was some overflow on one corner this עולה ola bird
is in the wrong place and it's with the חטאת chatat birds.
But you, very reasonably, assumed that it was a חטאת chatat and
you ate it. ואכלה, v'achala, and you ate it. פטור, patur, you're
exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan,
what does that teach us? דטועה בדבר מצוה פטור, deto'eh bidvar mitzvah
patur, that if you made an error when doing a מצוה mitzvah
you're exempt? היינו הך, hainu hach, that's exactly what we've been teaching
all along. הגמרא Hagemara says no, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might
have thought, התם הוא דטועה בדבר מצוה פטור, hatam hu deto'eh bidvar
mitzvah patur, היינו דעבד מצוה. hainu de'avad mitzvah. You made an error
in a מצוה mitzvah but eventually you actually were culminating in a
מצוה, mitzvah, you were going to take your לולב. lulav. אבל הכא
aval hacha here, דטעה בדבר מצוה, d'ta'ah b'devar mitzvah, you made an
error because you thought you were eating a חטאת chattas bird ולא
עבד מצוה, v'lo avad mitzvah, but it didn't culminate in doing the
מצוה. mitzvah. You were planning on doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but in
the end what you did was just an עבירה, aveira, right? You
understand the difference, right? In one case you actually are in the
process of taking לולב, lulav, it's just incidentally along the way you're
מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. Here, you never, you were wanting to do
a מצוה, mitzvah, but you were in the process of only doing
an עבירה aveira of eating an עולה, olah, not eating the חטאת.
chattas. So קא משמע לן kamashma lan that that doesn't matter, that
even if you're planning, even if you didn't culminate in a מצוה,
mitzvah, you're still exempt from the sin offering. מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll ask
you on this, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi Omer, השוחט את התמיד
שאינו מבוקר, hashocheit es hatamid she'eino mevukar, חייב חטאת. chayev chattas. It's
שבת Shabbos and you שחט shecht an animal for a תמיד tamid
for the daily sacrifice on שבת Shabbos that was not מבוקר mevukar
four days before from blemishes. בשבת, Bishabbos, and now even if it
winds up it had no blemish, if it did not go through
the process of being pre-checked, you're not יוצא. yotzei. And he says,
חייב חטאת. chayev chattas. You have to bring a חטאת. chattas. The
same רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi who normally says if you're doing a
מצוה mitzvah you're exempt if you accidentally violate שבת. Shabbos. וצריך תמיד
אחר Vetzarich tamid acher and obviously you have to bring another תמיד,
tamid, that's the whole point, you weren't יוצא. yotzei. So how do
you explain that? So maybe it's because you didn't in the end
do a מצוה, mitzvah, but you just got through saying that even
if it didn't culminate in a מצוה mitzvah you're still exempt. So
אמרי אבא מיניה דהיא, amrei aba minei dehi, forget that example. ואיתמר
עלה ve'itmar alah it was said on it, אמר רב שמואל בר
שילת amar Rav Shmuel bar Shilas אמר רב המנונא amar Rav Hamnuna
סבא Saba אמר רבי יצחק בר אשיאן amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ashyan
אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna אמר רב, amar Rav, so the
whole tradition in the name of רב, Rav, שהביאו מלשכה שאינו מבוקרים,
shehevi'o milishkah she'eino mevukarim, you brought it from the לשכה lishkah of
sheep that were not pre-checked sheep, which basically means it was your
own fault. That was a real negligence. We shouldn't say you were
distracted and preoccupied in the doing of a מצוה mitzvah and you
should be let off the hook because number one not only in
that case did you not end up doing a מצוה, mitzvah, which
maybe you could still get off the hook as we said, but
also you are highly negligent in the fact that you wound up
doing the wrong thing and therefore that by itself or the combination
of the two of not culminating a מצוה mitzvah עם im that
degree of negligence, that cannot exempt you. Okay, חזק. Chazak.